<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-08T14:55:41+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Thinh Q. Dinh</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quantum Computing Internships - 2024 Summer</title><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Computing Internships - 2024 Summer"/><published>2023-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep5/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="nvidia">Nvidia</h2> <p>One of the most exciting internships related to quantum computing is the Quantum Computing Software Intern opportunity at Nvidia. This internship offers students the chance to work on cutting-edge projects and contribute to the development of software for quantum computers. With the growing demand for expertise in this field, this internship is an excellent way to gain practical experience and make valuable connections in the industry.</p> <p>Quantum Computing Software Intern - Nvidia https://nvidia.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/NVIDIAExternalCareerSite/job/Quantum-Computing-Software-Intern_JR1973188</p> <h2 id="cisco">Cisco</h2> <p>Another fascinating opportunity is the internship at Cisco, where students can work on developing secure quantum communication protocols. This internship is a great opportunity for students to learn about the challenges and opportunities of building a quantum internet and contribute to the development of cutting-edge technology.</p> <p>Quantum Researcher PhD (Intern) - Cisco https://jobs.cisco.com/jobs/ProjectDetail/Quantum-Researcher-PhD-Intern-United-States/1405086?source=LinkedIn</p> <h2 id="bytedance">ByteDance</h2> <p>Bytedance, the Chinese multinational technology andEntertainment company, Incredible opportunities for interns to work on developing quantum chemistry software and explore the application of quantum computing in various fields.</p> <p>Intern in Quantum Chemistry - ByteDance https://jobs.bytedance.com/en/position/7270223451197540669/detail?spread=BSPP2KS</p> <h2 id="intel">Intel</h2> <p>At Intel, the Post Quantum Crypto Hardware Researcher Internship provides students with the chance to work on advanced research projects that are pushing the boundaries of quantum computing technology. With the increasing demand for secure communication protocols in the quantum era, this internship is an excellent way to gain practical experience in this field.</p> <p>Post Quantum Crypto Hardware Researcher Intern - Intel https://jobs.intel.com/en/job/-/-/599/55384436272</p> <h2 id="ibm">IBM</h2> <p>IBM’s Quantum Hardware Engineer Internship offers students the chance to work on cutting-edge projects revolving around the development of quantum hardware. This internship provides students with exposure to real-world applications of quantum computing and the opportunity to make valuable connections in the industry.</p> <p>Quantum Hardware Engineer - IBM https://careers.ibm.com/job/19232081/2024-summer-intern-quantum-hardware-engineer-remote/?codes=SN_LinkedIn&amp;Codes=SN_LinkedIn</p> <h2 id="xanadu">Xanadu</h2> <p>Xanadu, a startup in Canada, offers a residency program for students and recent graduates to work on advanced quantum computing research projects. The Xanadu residency program provides individuals with an opportunity to work with some of the brightest minds in the field and makes significant contributions to the development of quantum computing technology.</p> <p>Xanadu Residency Program https://xanadu.applytojob.com/apply/CPPWQlGLI3/Xanadu-Residency-Program-2024</p> <h2 id="jpmorgan">J.P.Morgan</h2> <p>Finally, the JP Morgan Intern Program offers individuals the chance to work on cutting-edge research projects and contribute to the development of the next generation of technology. With the growing demand for expertise in quantum computing, this internship is an excellent way to gain practical experience and make valuable connections in the industry.</p> <p>J.P.Morgan Intern Program https://careers.jpmorgan.com/global/en/students/programs/research-technologies-summer-associate-program</p>]]></content><author><name>Thinh Q. Dinh</name></author><category term="intern"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here are some exciting quantum computing internships currently available for students and recent graduates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ep 4. Recent Advances in Quantum Technologies (có bản Tiếng Việt)</title><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ep 4. Recent Advances in Quantum Technologies (có bản Tiếng Việt)"/><published>2023-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep4/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="quantum-computing">Quantum Computing</h2> <p>Quantum computers utilize quantum bits, or qubits, which can exist in multiple states at once due to quantum superposition, thereby potentially processing a higher volume of information more efficiently.</p> <p><strong>IBM</strong> offers cloud-based quantum computing services through their Q Experience platform, which allows researchers to run algorithms on their quantum processors which are up to 433 qubits (IBM Osprey) [1]. In 2019, <strong>Google</strong> announced their quantum processor Sycamore with 53 qubits had achieved “quantum supremacy” by sampling random circuits and solving a problem in 200 seconds that would take the most powerful supercomputer thousands of years [2]. Several other companies like <strong>IonQ</strong>, <strong>QuEra</strong>, and <strong>Xanadu</strong> are developing quantum processors with 32, 256, and 216 qubits, respectively [3]. While full scale quantum computers capable of practical applications are still years away, these advancements demonstrate potentials in <em>drug discovery</em>, <em>logistics</em>, <em>network optimization</em> and <em>machine learning</em>.</p> <figure> <img src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/206780f2af402a664c3e5be72000e8eb42f1e3b0/0_36_1721_1033/master/1721.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none"/> <figcaption>Fig 1: Sundar Pichai, pictured with the Sycamore Quantum processor. Photograph: Reuters</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="quantum-sensors">Quantum Sensors</h2> <p>Quantum sensors exploit quantum coherence to enhance sensor capabilities. The UK <strong>University of Birmingham</strong>’s quantum gravity gradiometer, for instance, uses quantum interference for precise measurement of tiny variations in gravitational fields [4]. This has applications in mineral and oil exploration, underground infrastructure mapping, and aquifers mapping.</p> <figure> <img src="https://www.photonics.com/images/Web/Articles/2022/3/4/REAS_Birmingham_Researchers_Report_First_Field_Use_of_Quantum_Gravity_Gradiometer_2.jpg"/> <figcaption>Fig 2: Gravity-based detection of ground conditions such as mine workings, tunnels, and unstable ground. Photograph: University of Birmingham</figcaption> </figure> <p>In Jan 2021, US Army scientists develop Ultra-broadband quantum receiver the first to analyze entire radio frequency spectrum from 0 up to 20 GHZ, detect AM, FM, Bluetooth and WiFi [5].</p> <h2 id="quantum-communications-and-networking">Quantum Communications and Networking</h2> <p>Quantum communication leverages quantum entanglement for highly secure information transfer. An excellent example is China’s <strong>Micius</strong> satellite sucessfully distributing quantum keys to ground stations near Vienna and Beijing, enabling a secure virtual meeting which are 7400 km apart [6].</p> <figure> <img src="https://news.univie.ac.at/typo3temp/pics/2d3695d4e9.jpg"/> <figcaption>Fig 3: Viena-Beijing QKD experiment. Photograph: ÖAW</figcaption> </figure> <p>In addition to the Micius success, other notable quantum communication networks include a land-based quantum key distribution link set up between Vienna and St Poelten, Austria using 200 km of standard fibre optic cable [7], as well as US DARPA quantum network [8].</p> <h2 id="điện-toán-lượng-tử">Điện toán lượng tử</h2> <p>Máy tính lượng tử sử dụng bit lượng tử hoặc qubit, có thể tồn tại ở nhiều trạng thái cùng một lúc do sự chồng chất lượng tử. Do đó, máy tính lượng tử có khả năng xử lý lượng thông tin cao hơn hiệu quả hơn máy tính truyền thống.</p> <p><strong>IBM</strong> hiện cung cấp dịch vụ điện toán lượng tử dựa trên đám mây thông qua nền tảng Q Experience, cho phép người dụng chạy thuật toán trên bộ xử lý lượng tử lên tới 433 qubit (IBM Osprey) [1]. Năm 2019, <strong>Google</strong> tuyên bố bộ xử lý lượng tử Sycamore với 53 qubit của họ đã đạt được “ưu thế lượng tử” bằng giải quyết một vấn đề trong 200 giây mà siêu máy tính mạnh nhất phải mất hàng nghìn năm [2]. Một số công ty khác như <strong>IonQ</strong>, <strong>QuEra</strong> và <strong>Xanadu</strong> đang phát triển bộ xử lý lượng tử với 32, 256 và 216 qubit tương ứng [3]. Mặc dù, máy tính lượng tử hoàn thiện có khả năng ứng dụng thực tế vẫn còn nhiều năm nữa mới có, nhưng những tiến bộ này thể hiện tiềm năng trong <em>khám phá thuốc</em>, <em>vận tải</em>, <em>tối ưu hóa mạng</em> và <em>học máy</em>.</p> <figure> <img src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/206780f2af402a664c3e5be72000e8eb42f1e3b0/0_36_1721_1033/master/1721.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none"/> <figcaption>Hình 1: Sundar Pichai, trong hình với bộ xử lý Sycamore Quantum. Ảnh: Reuters</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="cảm-biến-lượng-tử">Cảm biến lượng tử</h2> <p>Cảm biến lượng tử khai thác coherence lượng tử để nâng cao khả năng của cảm biến. Ví dụ, máy đo trọng sai lượng tử của Đại học Birmingham** của Vương quốc Anh sử dụng giao thoa lượng tử để đo chính xác những biến đổi nhỏ trong trường hấp dẫn [4]. Điều này có ứng dụng trong thăm dò khoáng sản và dầu mỏ, lập bản đồ cơ sở hạ tầng dưới lòng đất và lập bản đồ tầng nước.</p> <figure> <img src="https://www.photonics.com/images/Web/Articles/2022/3/4/REAS_Birmingham_Researchers_Report_First_Field_Use_of_Quantum_Gravity_Gradiometer_2.jpg"/> <figcaption>Hình 2: Phát hiện các điều kiện mặt đất dựa trên trọng lực như hoạt động khai thác mỏ, đường hầm và mặt đất không ổn định. Ảnh: Đại học Birmingham</figcaption> </figure> <p>Vào tháng 1 năm 2021, các nhà khoa học của Quân đội Hoa Kỳ đã phát triển máy thu lượng tử siêu băng thông rộng đầu tiên để phân tích toàn bộ phổ tần số vô tuyến từ 0 đến 20 GHZ, phát hiện AM, FM, Bluetooth và WiFi [5].</p> <h2 id="mạng-và-truyền-thông-lượng-tử">Mạng và Truyền thông Lượng tử</h2> <p>Truyền thông lượng tử tận dụng sự rối lượng tử để truyền thông tin có độ an toàn cao. Một ví dụ điển hình là vệ tinh <strong>Micius</strong> của Trung Quốc đã phân phối thành công khóa lượng tử đến các trạm mặt đất gần Vienna và Bắc Kinh, tạo điều kiện cho một cuộc họp ảo an toàn cách nhau 7400 km [6].</p> <figure> <img src="https://news.univie.ac.at/typo3temp/pics/2d3695d4e9.jpg"/> <figcaption>Hình 3: Thí nghiệm QKD Viena-Bắc Kinh. Ảnh: ÖAW</figcaption> </figure> <p>Ngoài thành công của Micius, các mạng truyền thông lượng tử đáng chú ý khác bao gồm hệ thống phân phối khóa lượng tử trên đất liền được thiết lập giữa Vienna và St Poelten, Áo sử dụng 200 km cáp quang tiêu chuẩn [7], cũng như mạng lượng tử DARPA của Hoa Kỳ [8].</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] IBM,”IBM Unveils 400 Qubit-Plus Quantum Processor and Next-Generation IBM Quantum System Two”,URL: https://newsroom.ibm.com/2022-11-09-IBM-Unveils-400-Qubit-Plus-Quantum-Processor-and-Next-Generation-IBM-Quantum-System-Two</p> <p>[2] Google, “Quantum Supremacy Using a Programmable Superconducting Processor”, URL:https://blog.research.google/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-using-programmable.html</p> <p>[3] Wikipedia, “List of quantum processors”, URL: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_quantum_processors</p> <p>[4] UBirmingham,”Sensor breakthrough paves way for groundbreaking map of world under Earth surface”, URL: https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/news/2022/sensor-breakthrough-paves-way-for-groundbreaking-map-of-world-under-earth-surface</p> <p>[5] IDST.”Militaries developing Quantum receiver employing Rydberg atoms”,URL: https://idstch.com/technology/quantum/militaries-developing-quantum-receiver-employing-rydberg-atoms-for-ultrasensitive-ultrawideband-and-fast-soldier-communications/</p> <p>[6] PhysicsWorld, “Beijing and Vienna have a quantum conversation”, URL: https://physicsworld.com/a/beijing-and-vienna-have-a-quantum-conversation/</p> <p>[7] BBC, “‘Unbreakable’ encryption unveiled”, URL: http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/7661311.stm</p> <p>[8] “DARPA quantum network: A brief history”, URL: https://www.aliroquantum.com/blog/darpa-quantum-network-a-brief-history</p>]]></content><author><name>Thinh Q. Dinh</name></author><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum technologies have moved from science fiction to reality, opening up new possibilities in various fields. Thankfully, you don't need to be a quantum physicist to understand quantum technologies. All you need to know is that quantum technologies are tools and techniques that take advantage of the weird and wonderful rules of quantum physics to do something useful.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ep 3. Introduction to Quantum Libraries</title><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ep 3. Introduction to Quantum Libraries"/><published>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep3/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="quantum-market">Quantum Market</h2> <p>In the quantum market, numerous tech giants and startups have developed comprehensive libraries for Quantum Computing. This includes but not limited to Google’s Cirq, Rigetti’s Forest, IBM’s Qiskit, and Xanadu’s Pennylane, each built with their unique advantages and capabilities. Two notable libraries are <strong>IBM’s Qiskit</strong> and <strong>Xanadu’s PennyLane</strong>.</p> <h2 id="ibms-qiskit">IBM’s Qiskit</h2> <p>Qiskit, provided by IBM, offers a robust and user-friendly platform for quantum computing – from writing quantum programs to executing them on simulated or real quantum hardware. It is accessible and feature-rich, making quantum experimentation more feasible.</p> <p>To install Qiskit, you need a Python environment and you can install it via pip:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="err">!</span><span class="n">pip</span> <span class="n">install</span> <span class="n">qiskit</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Let’s create a simple quantum circuit with Qiskit:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="n">qiskit</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">QuantumCircuit</span>

<span class="c1"># Initialize a quantum circuit with 2 qubits
</span><span class="n">qc</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">QuantumCircuit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Apply a Hadamard gate to the first qubit
</span><span class="n">qc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">h</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Apply a CNOT gate
</span><span class="n">qc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">cx</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Visualize the circuit
</span><span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">qc</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="xanadus-pennylane">Xanadu’s PennyLane</h2> <p>PennyLane, provided by Xanadu, is another powerful quantum library that promotes quantum machine learning by integrating with existing machine learning libraries. Its hybrid quantum-classical computations capability is a game-changer.</p> <p>You can install PennyLane via pip:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="err">!</span><span class="n">pip</span> <span class="n">install</span> <span class="n">pennylane</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Let’s create a simple quantum circuit with PennyLane:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">pennylane</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">qml</span>

<span class="c1"># Create a device to execute the circuit
</span><span class="n">dev</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">device</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">default.qubit</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">wires</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="nd">@qml.qnode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">dev</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">quantum_circuit</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Hadamard</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">wires</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">CNOT</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">wires</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">expval</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">PauliZ</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">@</span> <span class="n">qml</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">PauliZ</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span>

<span class="n">result</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">quantum_circuit</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">result</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="why-use-these-quantum-libraries">Why Use These Quantum Libraries</h2> <p>There are several reasons why IBM’s Qiskit and Xanadu’s Pennylane stand out among the many quantum libraries:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Ease of Use:</strong> Both Qiskit and PennyLane are designed with user-friendly interfaces, making them accessible for beginners and experts alike.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Interoperability:</strong> Particularly with PennyLane’s focus on quantum machine learning, these libraries can smoothly interact with classic machine learning tools, fostering the creation of hybrid algorithms.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Versatility:</strong> PennyLane distinguishes itself with its versatile capabilities and seamless integration with various quantum service providers. It supports various systems ranging from IonQ, IBMQ, and Rigetti to GPU-based quantum simulators from NVIDIA. On the other hand, Qiskit is deeply integrated with IBM’s ecosystem, providing full support and access to IBM’s advanced quantum computers. This ensures optimized performances and features when operating on IBM’s quantum hardware.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Community Support:</strong> Both libraries are open-source and have strong community support, offering rich resources and opportunities for collaborative development.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Robust Documentation and Tutorials:</strong> Both Qiskit and PennyLane have extensive documentation and offer tutorials that ease the learning process for developers venturing into quantum programming.</p> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Thinh Q. Dinh</name></author><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum computing is an exciting growing field! Hence, a lot of libs are being developed to make it easy for anyone to get into quantum computing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ep 2. Basics of Quantum Physics for Quantum Computing</title><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ep 2. Basics of Quantum Physics for Quantum Computing"/><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep2/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="quantum-states-mixed-state-and-pure-state">Quantum States: Mixed State and Pure State</h2> <p>In quantum mechanics, <strong>quantum states</strong> or state vector is a fundamental concept. It refers to the state of a quantum system and includes all the information you can know about it. Quantum state are described by either a <strong>mixed state</strong> or a <strong>pure state</strong>. While a <strong>pure state</strong> is a quantum state that is described by a single state vector (a precisely defined wave function), a <strong>mixed state</strong> describes a statistical mix of possible states. Both of these present a different contextual understanding of a system’s state.</p> <p>When it comes to a pure state, it is usually represented by precise wave function detailing a cohesive superposition of values. On the other hand, a mixed state is usually the result of lack of perfect information about a system, often represented by a density matrix rather than a wave function.</p> <h2 id="quantum-superposition">Quantum Superposition</h2> <p>One of the most important quantum principles is <strong>superposition</strong>. This refers to how subatomic particles can exist in multiple states at once. For example, a qubit can represent a 0, 1, or both 0 and 1 simultaneously due to superposition. This differs radically from classical bits that can only be in a 0 or 1 state. Superposition enables qubits to process significantly more information in parallel than classical bits.</p> <figure> <img src="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/I-Putu-Agus-Eka-Pratama/publication/365122869/figure/fig1/AS:11431281145671860@1681440876250/Superposition-in-quantum-computing.png"/> <figcaption>Fig 1: An illustration depicting quantum superposition.</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="measurement-and-collapse">Measurement and Collapse</h2> <p><strong>Measurement</strong> is a fundamental aspect of quantum computing that relies on the principle of wavefunction collapse. The wavefunction represents the probability distribution of a quantum system, describing the possible states it can be in. When a measurement is made on a qubit in superposition, the wavefunction collapses into a specific state of either 0 or 1. This collapse is random, with the probability of each outcome determined by the amplitudes of the superposed states.</p> <h2 id="quantum-entanglement">Quantum Entanglement</h2> <p>Another vital quantum phenomenon is <strong>entanglement</strong>. This occurs when multiple quantum particles become correlated such that their states rely on each other, regardless of physical distance separating them. Entangled qubits retain connections and can instantaneously influence each other’s states. This enables quantum computers to process and transfer information with unprecedented efficiency.</p> <figure> <img src="https://quantumatlas.umd.edu/static/entanglement_chart-c1972bded042d9571e841ee153e5d690.png" width="100"/> <figcaption>Fig 2: An illustration depicting quantum entanglement.</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="quantum-coherence">Quantum Coherence</h2> <p>In the context of quantum computing, <strong>coherence</strong> refers to the ability of qubits to maintain their state of superposition. During this period, qubits exhibit wave-like behaviour and can interact with each other through quantum gates. When qubits are in coherence, quantum operations can take place efficiently. However, maintaining quantum coherence for longer durations is a major challenge in quantum computing due to environmental noise and other factors that can cause qubits to lose their quantum mechanical properties.</p> <h2 id="quantum-decoherence">Quantum Decoherence</h2> <p>Quantum computers are highly sensitive systems that are prone to environmental interference, leading to <strong>quantum decoherence</strong>. Decoherence refers to the loss of quantum coherence caused by interactions with the external environment. This can lead to errors in quantum computations and is one of the primary obstacles in developing practical quantum computers.</p>]]></content><author><name>Thinh Q. Dinh</name></author><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum computing relies heavily on principles of quantum physics to achieve its enhanced computational capabilities. Grasping some core quantum concepts is key to comprehending quantum computing on a deeper level.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ep 1. Introduction to Quantum Computing</title><link href="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ep 1. Introduction to Quantum Computing"/><published>2023-09-29T22:11:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-29T22:11:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thinhqdinh.github.io/blog/2023/ep1/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="understanding-quantum-computing">Understanding Quantum Computing</h2> <p>Quantum computing is an innovative technology that harnesses the principles of quantum mechanics to process information. It differs markedly from classical computing, enabling calculations to be processed in new and powerful ways.</p> <h3 id="how-quantum-computing-differs-from-classical-computing">How Quantum Computing Differs from Classical Computing</h3> <figure> <img src="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Zahid-Hussain-63/publication/308414229/figure/fig2/AS:669710362353681@1536682801640/Figure-1-Classical-Bit-Vs-Qubit.ppm"/> <figcaption>Fig 1: Classical Bit vs Quantum Bit.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Classical computing is based on binary digits, or “bits,” that represent either a 0 or a 1. By contrast, quantum computing uses quantum, or “qubits.” A qubit can be both 0 and 1 simultaneously, thanks to the quantum property called superposition. This allows quantum computers to process a high number of possibilities at once.</p> <p>Additionally, qubits can be entangled due to another quantum property called entanglement. When qubits are entangled, the state of one qubit can instantaneously affect the state of another, no matter how far apart they are. This enhances the computational speed and power of computers significantly.</p> <h3 id="key-terms-and-concepts-in-quantum-computing">Key Terms and Concepts in Quantum Computing</h3> <p>In order to fully understand quantum computing, it’s essential to grasp a few key concepts:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Qubit:</strong> The basic unit of quantum information, which can be both 0 and 1 at the same time due to superposition.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Superposition:</strong> A quantum state where a system can be in multiple states simultaneously.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Entanglement:</strong> The phenomenon where the state of one qubit is directly related to the state of another, no matter the distance separating them.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Quantum Gates:</strong> Basic quantum circuits that operate on a small number of qubits. They perform the actual computation in a quantum system. Just like logic gates in classical circuits, quantum gates are a primary building block of quantum computing.</p> </li> </ul> <figure> <img src="https://www.lancaster.ac.uk/staff/schomeru/lecturenotes/Quantum%20Information%20Processing/qgates.png"/> <figcaption>Fig 2: Different Types of Quantum Gates.</figcaption> </figure> <ul> <li><strong>Quantum Circuits:</strong> A sequence of quantum gates. They describe quantum computations and are used to manipulate qubits. You can think of them as the quantum version of classical computing circuits.</li> </ul> <figure> <img src="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Ritu-Kapur/publication/348690539/figure/fig2/AS:982847284314123@1611340461981/An-example-quantum-circuit-developed-using-IBMs-quantum-computing-simulator.ppm"/> <figcaption>Fig 3: A Example of Quantum Circuit.</figcaption> </figure> <ul> <li><strong>Quantum Interference:</strong> Another key concept explaining how probability amplitudes can add up to reinforce or cancel each other, creating the effect of interference. This is key for quantum algorithms.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Thinh Q. Dinh</name></author><category term="Quantum"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum computing is a fascinating and complex subject. This article will serve as an introductory guide, designed to usher beginners into this field.]]></summary></entry></feed>